<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-10-26T15:46:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Removing lein packages from local repo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/10/26/removing-lein-packages-from-local-repo.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/10/26/removing-lein-packages-from-local-repo.html</id>
    <published>2015-10-26T15:46:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-26T15:47:16-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm -rf /.m2/repository/packagename&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perlin noise (naive &amp; slow) literate programming example</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/10/26/perlin-noise-naive-slow-literate-programming-example.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/10/26/perlin-noise-naive-slow-literate-programming-example.html</id>
    <published>2015-10-26T10:22:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-26T14:54:34-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Perlin Noise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/noise.html"&gt;View the source with documenation&lt;/a&gt;, generated by Marginalia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Clojure implementation of Perlin noise.  Slow, naive, and possibly otherwise flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried for about 6 hours to get Marginalia to handle comments inside of forms, without success.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Connecting Figwheel to Emacs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/10/25/Connecting-Figwheel-to-Emacs.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/10/25/Connecting-Figwheel-to-Emacs.html</id>
    <published>2015-10-25T14:18:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-25T14:32:58-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have the lein-fighweel plugin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have nrepl port set (mine is 7888)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;lein repl :connect 7888&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Emacs, run &lt;code&gt;cider-connect&lt;/code&gt;, choose &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;, and type the port (7888)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that repl, &lt;code&gt;(use &amp;#39;figwheel-sidecar.repl-api)&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;(cljs-repl)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;cider-jack-in&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Load page in browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;(in-ns your-ns.core)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The German Tank Problem For Competitive Intel</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/09/26/german-tank-problem-for-competitive-intel.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/09/26/german-tank-problem-for-competitive-intel.html</id>
    <published>2015-09-25T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-25T14:52:16-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The German Tank Problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Or Why To Obfuscate Your User IDs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(note, this is pulled largely from the Wikipedia page, where there is additional derivation
of these equations.  This post started as an exercise in understanding by explaining, and ended
as an exercise in learning LaTex and seeing how high I could raise my blood pressure)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In World War II, Allied intelligence used conventional intelligence and statistical
estimation to try to guess the production of German tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistical estimates, which were based on a handful of serial numbers from
captured tanks, turned out to be much, much more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a frequentist perspective, this estimation is given by the formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[N = m + {m - k \over k}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where m is the max serial number from the sample, and k is the size of the sample.
Intuitively, this is sample maximum plus the average gap between observations in the sample&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Bayesian analysis yields a probability mass function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[P(N = n) =
\begin{cases}
  0 &amp;amp; \quad \text{if } n &amp;lt; m\cr
  {k -1 \over k} {{ m - 1 \choose k - 1 } \over { n \choose k }} &amp;amp; \quad \text{otherwise}
\end{cases}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A probability mass function differs from a probability density function (pdf) in that the latter is associated with continuous rather than discrete random variables; the values of the latter are not probabilities as such: a pdf must be integrated over an interval to yield a probability.  (source: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this we can get the mean and standard deviation of the distribution in order to estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[N \approx \mu \pm \sigma \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mean of a probability distribution is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\mu = \sum_{\substack{x}} xP(x)\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: in wikipedia, this is referred to as &amp;ldquo;order of magnitude&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; why?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in this case it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[\mu = \sum_{\substack{n}} n \times (N = n \text{ | } M = m, K = k) \]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, so what&amp;rsquo;s the probability that N = n, given m and k?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditional probability tells us that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[(n | m,k) = (m | n,k){(n | k) \over (m | k)}\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first term on the right-hand side is the probability that the max serial number
is equal to m, when n is known&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numerator of the second term is the credibility that the total number of tanks
is equal to n when k tanks have been observed but before the serial numbers have
been observed. Assume that it has a discrete uniform distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The denominator is  the probability that the maximum serial number is equal to m
once k tanks have been observed but before the serial numbers have actually been observed.
\scriptstyle (m\mid k) can be re-written in terms of the other quantities by marginalizing
over all possible \scriptstyle n.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For k &amp;gt;= 4, there are formulas to get the mean and standard deviation (see wikipedia for derivation)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resume Inspired by Chris Wanstrath</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/09/23/wanstrath-style-resume.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/09/23/wanstrath-style-resume.html</id>
    <published>2015-09-22T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-09-25T14:23:10-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The resume format is so awful. Resumes should be: What I&amp;rsquo;m interested in, what I&amp;rsquo;m good at, and why I&amp;rsquo;m good at it.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Chris Wanstrath (@defunkt) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/defunkt/status/183409973341065216"&gt;March 24, 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m interested in&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small team with a single vision that drives them.  A team that has fun together,
because they do things that amaze each other, where every individual looks forward to getting the next
pull request.  A small team that invests time in thinking, in tools, and in experimentation by prototyping.
I believe these investments are time savers and force multipliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically (and as of September 2015), I&amp;rsquo;m interested in these technologies, which I believe are the
fruits of such teams and values, and will enable small, productive, less fragmented engineering teams in the coming years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional programming in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immutable data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The confluence of the above in Clojure, Clojurescript, React.js&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GraphQL / Falcor style alternatives to REST&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning (and digging into math and algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probablistic thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generative testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disposable infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data visualization (and digging into computer graphics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognitive biases, especially in the realm of doing and managing software development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert at any of these things, but I&amp;rsquo;m rapidly getting better at understanding and
applying the first three, and spending a lot of time building my fundamental base for the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m good at&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building and strengthening an engineering team.  Breaking down problems (or sometimes
finding better questions).  I&amp;rsquo;m good at Ruby on Rails and JavaScript. I&amp;rsquo;m a good communicator, especially in
written forms (this may not be evident from this blog, but I like to think I usually have the right touch in a lot of
startup-related contexts, like email, chat, one-on-ones, code review, etc). I&amp;rsquo;m pretty good at, and trying to
get better at, systems thinking.  I&amp;rsquo;m good at working with partial or fully remote teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m good at it&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve worked at big companies and small; rolling in cash, and rolling towards the end of the runway.
I&amp;rsquo;ve had the good fortune to work with some truly excellent technologists and gifted leaders, and during my
time as a systems auditor for PriceWaterhouseCoopers, get an inside look at great work environments and stifling ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a programmer, I&amp;rsquo;ve put in the time. Innumerable late nights down the rabbit hole because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t
stop until it worked, then back again in the morning, if necessary (as it often was), until I understood it. Biting
off more than I could chew, and making it work. Battles with Linux servers. Debugging under pressure. Hotfixes.
All of the above after a page at 11pm New Year Eve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning about version control, testing, and processes so I could put my cowboy hat away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been at it long enough to understand that tech is a fashion business, and learn when to buy the latest
trend and how to avoid tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s bell-bottoms (most of the time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I taught a three month intensive class on web
development, and this made me better at tailoring my feedback to individuals, being patient, and illustrating
concepts with relevant examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read, all the time, as much as I can. As many books &amp;ndash; technical, historical, and sociological &amp;ndash; as I can digest.
I keep up with people on the cutting edge and try to learn about the giants on whose shoulders they stand.
I love this stuff and am plugged into this culture, but I&amp;rsquo;m not so narrow that I can&amp;rsquo;t tell which parts are childish and toxic, and I
know when to unplug, go home, and recharge.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Copying a table from Heroku Postgres to local csv file</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2014/12/24/copying-a-table-from-heroku-postgres-to-local-csv-file.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2014/12/24/copying-a-table-from-heroku-postgres-to-local-csv-file.html</id>
    <published>2014-12-23T21:57:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-12-23T21:58:57-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="highlight plaintext"&gt;echo "COPY products TO STDOUT WITH CSV HEADER " | heroku pg:psql -a app-name &amp;gt; products.csv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
